so let's see how do we access the
magnetic discs and how long does it take
to get to our data we will assume that
the dis is already spinning if the disc
is not spinning it takes possibly
several seconds to actually spin up the
discs so most of the time if you're
accessing our data frequently the disc
would just keep spinning so if the dis
is spinning then the access time
consists of the seek time which is the
time it takes to move the head assembly
to the correct cylinder for our data so
we know where the data is we know which
cylinder which sector which surface we
first have to get the heads so that they
are above the correct cylinder so at
that point one of the heads will be
above the track where our data really is
next there is the rotational latency
after we have moved the heads there's
somewhere along the track but not
necessarily and usually not above the
very sector that we interested in so the
rotational latency is about waiting for
the start of our sector to finally get
under the head that will read it not
that the head is actually sitting in one
place at this point but the platter is
rotating so different parts of the track
are getting under the head and the
rotational latenci is how long until the
beginning of our sector gets under the
head next we have the data read which
which is we read until the end of the
sector is seen by the head again the
data read really depends on how fast the
dis is spinning and how many sectors we
have per track for example if the whole
track is just one sector then the data
read will be a whole rotation of the dis
if we have 10 sectors per track then the
data read will be 1/10th of a rotation
then there is some controller time for
the this controller to actually check
the check sum determine that the sector
is okay and so on and the iob bus time
which is once the dis drive itself and
it's controller have the data how long
does it take to actually get that data
to the main memory now note that unlike
a cash or a dam where we could actually
be doing multiple axises potentially at
the same time on a magnetic disc once we
seek to one track we cannot really be
reading the other tracks so really what
happens is accesses to the disk are
happening one at a time we go to a track
possibly read several sectors but we
cannot access another track until we are
done with this one and move to the next
track so all of this is the latency to
do one disk access and often times the
latency of a disk request made by the
operating system includes this plus a
significant queuing delay because we
first have to wait for previous axis is
to finish doing this and only then our
axis can move the heads to the correct
position and do a read or a write